Guide to the Randall Smith Spanish Civil War Correspondence ALBA.100
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Randall Smith Spanish Civil War Correspondence
1937-1942
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Smith, Randall, 1917-1989
ALBA.100
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Randall Smith (1917-1989) was an ambulance driver in Spain during the Spanish Civil War. After the war he lived in California where be became a longshoreman and a seaman, as well as an active member of the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and the National Maritime Union. Later, Smith moved to New York City and worked as a marketing executive. This collection includes letters written by Randall Smith to his mother and sister while an American volunteer in the Spanish Civil War.
Provenance
The Randall Smith collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Randall (Pete) Smith (1917-1989) was born in Pennsylvania to a family whose roots lead back to Colonial America. For generations, both sides of his family lived and worked on farms in the Pennsylvania and New Jersey region, but his parents broke that tradition by becoming doctors (both in general practice and obstetrics). The Smith family settled in South Fork, PA and later moved to Warren, Ohio. Smith had a brother, Mike, and two sisters, Margaret and Isabel. He graduated from Harding High School in Warren, Ohio then moved to New York City where he befriended members of the Communist Party. He became a party organizer in Ohio for a brief time and at the age of 21 joined the fight in Spain. Smith sailed to France on the President Roosevelt in March of 1937 and arrived in Spain in July of 1937 via the Pyrenees. He was an ambulance driver with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade while stationed at various sites throughout the country, including Barcelona, Albacete and the region of Catalonia. Smith was wounded twice, the second time at the battle at the Ebro River, and returned to the United States in December 1938 after recovering from his second injury. In 1976, Smith organized a historical commission under the auspices of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade for the purposes of gathering and preserving archives, oral histories, and graphic material related to veterans of the Spanish Civil War.
Smith married upon his return from Spain, and lived in San Francisco, Los Angeles, and New York City. He worked as a longshoreman with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU), volunteered for the Merchant Marines during World War II, and joined the National Maritime Union (NMU). After holding various jobs in the Los Angeles area, he received his MBA degree from UCLA. Smith worked for various companies as a marketing executive and retired from the Edison Electric Institute in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains letters from Smith to his mother (Elizabeth, nee Cisney) and sister (Isabel) written while in Spain (August 1937 until December 1938) and just after his return. The letters from Spain contain Smith's thoughts on international politics and his decision to go to Spain, personal matters regarding his family and friends, activity on the front as an ambulance driver, stories of his friend, Walter Schuetrum and brigade commissar, Dave Doran, as well as notes on the Spanish cuisine and countryside. The letters after his return focus on the job and real estate market of the United States of the early 1940s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence and Related Clippings, 1937-1942.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Randall Smith Papers: Records of the VALB Historical Commission ALBA #3
Manny Harriman Video Oral History Project ALBA Video #48
Barcelona (Spain); Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Catalonia (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Valencia (Spain); Correspondence.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Foreign public opinion.; Albacete (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Schuetrum, Walter.; Doran, Dave, 1910-1938
- Series I: Correspondence and Related Clippings, 1937-1942
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother and Sister (Isabel), Aug - Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother and Sister (Isabel), Jan-Jun 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother and Sister (Isabel), Jul - Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother, Sep - Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother and Sister (Isabel), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother, [circa 1939 - 1941] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: From R.S. to Mother, Jun 1, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Transcript of Letter from R.S. to Family, Sept (?) 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Transcript of Letters from R.S. to Family, Feb 2, Mar 5, & Sept 5 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings re: R.S. (Photocopies), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)